All India Trade Union Congress Archives
International Institute of Social History
- Secretariat of AITUC, 1957-61
  - Messages
    - 12-5-60 Letter to The Secretary, AITUC and his reply, Invitation, 1960; 5.1274.17
      English; Palghat
    - 26-5-60 Letter to Com. S.A.Dange, General Secretary, AITUC, 1960; 5.1274.18
    - 20-5-60 Letter to Secretary, Palghat Dist. P.W.D.Workers Union, 1960; 5.1274.19
    - 27-5-60 Letter to The Secretary, AITUC, 1960; 5.1274.20
    - 6-6-60 Letter to The Secretary, AITUC, 1960; 5.1274.21
      English; Kollegal
    - 9-6-60 Invitation and its Descriptions and reply by K.G.Srivastav, Secretary, AITUC, 1960; 5.1274.22
    - 20-6-60 Invitation for 1st Conference of Maharastra State Hotel Kaamgar Union and reply by K.G.Srivastav, Secretary, AITUC, 1960; 5.1274.23
      English / Hindi; Bambay
  - Correspondence from Office Bearers
    Correspondence between various AITUC leaders like Indrajit Gupta, S. A. Dange, M. Atchutan, K.G. Shrivastava, S.S. Mirajkar, M.K. Pandhe on issues ranging from organisational matters, workers' struggle and victamisation, general council and working committee meeting to industrial cases, industrial disputes and annual conferences of unions.
    - Correspondence in the month of December 1959, 5.1291.1
    - Correspondence in the month of January 1960, 5.1291.2
    - Correspondence in the month of February 1960, 5.1291.3
    - Correspondence in the month of March, 1960; 5.1291.4
    - Correspondence in the month of April, 1960; 5.1291.5
    - Correspondence in the month of May, 1960; 5.1291.6
    - Correspondence in the month of June, 1960; 5.1291.7
    - Correspondence in the month of July, 1960; 5.1291.8
    - Correspondence in the month of August, 1960; 5.1291.9
    - Correspondence in the month of September, 1960; 5.1291.10
    - Correspondence in the month of October, 1960; 5.1291.11
    - Correspondence in the month of November, 1960; 5.1291.12
    - Correspondence in the month of December, 1960; 5.1291.13
  - Com. Dange (Party File) AITUC Center Sect. 1956-57
    Meeting of the railway sub-committee of the AITUC; Organisational report of AITUC in Ranigung coal belt by Kalyan Roy; Papers and letters addressed S.A. Dange ranging from election results in states, publication of literature to organisational and union matters by different state and district committees.
    - Minutes of the Meeting and related Documents in the month of June, 1956; 5.1000.1
    - 31-7-56 Agenda Railways Sub-Committee Met in the month of July, 1956; 5.1000.2
    - 18-9-56 Letter and Documents Regarding Ben Bradley in the month of September, 1956; 5.1000.3
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of October, 1956; 5.1000.4
    - Correspondence and Other Documents for the month of November, 1956; 5.1000.5
    - Correspondence in the month of December, 1956; 5.1000.6
    - Correspondence in the month of January, 1957; 5.1000.7
    - Correspondence in the month of February, 1957; 5.1000.8
    - Correspondence in the month of March, 1957; 5.1000.9
    - Correspondence in the month of April, 1957; 5.1000.10
    - 20-5-57 "Organisation Regard" By - Kalyan Roy in the month of May, 1957; 5.1000.11
    - Correspondence of Election Commission of India and others for the month of June, 1957; 5.1000.12
  - 16th Session of Standing Committee on Labour 1958
    Note on the agenda for the E & I committee; Note on the requirement of hospital for insured persons at Kanpur; Documents related to the 17th session of the standing committee on labour, 1958.
    - Note on Various Issues througth Item no., 1958; 5.1001.1
    - Hospital for Insured Persons at Kanpur, 1958; 5.1001.2
    - 21-6-58 Letter to Shri R.C.Saksena, Under Secrt. Mint. of Labour & Empoyment, 1958; 5.1001.3
    - 10-9-58 Letter to Shri R.C.Saksena, Under Secrt. Mint. of Labour & Empoyment, 1958; 5.1001.4
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of October, 1958; 5.1001.5
  - Ministry of Labour Documents & Letters with AITUC
    Papers on Wage Policy publiched by the Ministry of Labour and Employment; Correspondence and documents related to the first meeting of sterring group on wages.
    - Some Papers on Wage Policy, Mint. of Labour and Employment, 1957; 5.1002.1
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of December, 1957; 5.1002.2
    - Correspondence in the month of November, 1957; 5.1002.3
  - AITUC center Corresspondence, 1958
    Correspondence between AITUC centre and Secretary fo Metal Labour Union, Shoranur; Documents of Metal Labour Union, Shoranur related to closure of factories; Copy of LOK Sabha Ajournment motion.
    - 8-7-58 Letter to Secretary, Metal Labour Union, 1958; 5.1003.1
    - 29-6-58 Letter to The Secreatry, AITUC, 1958; 5.1003.2
      English; Shoranur, Kerala
    - 7-7-58 Letter to Dr. S.B.L.Nigam Assistant Economic Adviser, Mint. of Labour & Employment, 1958; 5.1003.3
    - Factories Threatened with Closure in Shoranur, Kerala, 1958; 5.1003.4
    - Copy of Lok Sabha, Adjournment Motion, 1958; 5.1003.5
  - Party-II
    Correspondence between S.A. Dange and CPI Darjeeling District committee; Press statement issued by Bhupesh Gupta; Birthday greetings to S.A. Dange from CPGB and others; Circular of CPI CEC meeting; Press statement issued by the secretariat of the National council of the CPI; Documents related to the border conflict with China
    - 6-4-59 Correspondence in the month of April, 1959; 5.95.1
    - Letter to Com. K.G.Srivastava Secreatry, AITUC Centre, 1959; 5.95.2
    - Correspondence in the month of September, 1959; 5.95.3
      English; New Delhi, London
    - Correspondence in the month of October, 1959; 5.95.4
      English; New Delhi / Madras
    - 24 & 29-10-59 Statements and Details, 1959; 5.95.5
    - Correspondence in the month of November, 1959; 5.95.6
      English; New Delhi, Kerala
    - Correspondence in the month of December, 1959; 5.95.7
    - Questions and Reply - By Iwars P. Morgan, American Broadcasting Company and Details, 1959; 5.95.8
  - Workers Part Management & Code of Discipline
    Notes on review of the working of the code of discipline, workers' participation in management through joint councils; Report of the tripartite committee, New Delhi 1959; Speeches of Guljari Lal Nanda, Minister of Labour and Employment; Seminar on the labour management cooperation, Feb. 1960; Article on labour-management co-operation by B.N. Datar; Observation of the study group of the Bombay management association.
    - 1-7-59 Indian Labour Confrence, Supplementary Memorundum-V, 1959; 5.1005.1
    - 30-9-59 Speech of Shri G.L.Nanda, Mint. of Labour & Employment, 1959; 5.1005.2
    - 30-11-59 The Meeting of the tripartitee to go into the functions of works Committees, 1959; 5.1005.3
    - Correspondence in the month of November, 1959; 5.1005.4
    - Correspondence in the month of January, 1960; 5.1005.5
    - Correspondence in the month of February, 1960; 5.1005.6
    - 12-7-60 Letter to The President, AITUC, 1960; 5.1005.7
    - Letter to Dear Com. M.S. Krishnan, 1960; 5.1005.8
    - Labour-Management Co-operation, 1960; 5.1005.9
    - 9-3-60 Labour Participation Managment Extension of Scheme Urged at Seminar, 1960; 5.1005.10
    - 4-3-60 Letter to The President, AITUC, 1960; 5.1005.11
    - 9-3-60 List of Participants in the IInd Seminar on labour Management Coopration, 1960; 5.1005.12
    - Workers Particitation in Management and Appendix, 1960; 5.1005.13
    - Observations of the study group of the Bombay Management Association, 1960; 5.1005.14
    - Section Inaugural Address by Shri Gulzarilal Nanda, Union Minster for Labour & Empoyment, 1960; 5.1005.15
  - Indian Labour Confference, 1958
    Note on the sixteenth tripartite Indian Labour Conference, 1958; Note on the praposed amendmens in the industrial disputes act; Correspondence between G.L. Nanda and S.A. Dange; Correspondence regarding recognising a union.
    - 2-8-58 Introduction, The 16th Tripartite Indian Labour Conference, 1958; 5.1006.1
    - Annexure B, 1958; 5.1006.2
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of May, 1958; 5.1006.3
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of June, 1958; 5.1006.4
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of August, 1958; 5.1006.5
    - 15-10-58 Letter to The Secretary, AITUC, 1958; 5.1006.6
  - CPI & AITUC
    Discussions related to the constitution of the AITUC; CPI circulars regarding Andhra Pradesh conference and english literary magazine; Documents related to the, conference, general body meeting, division of responsibilties and functioning of party heaquarter branch (PHQ) of Communist Party of India; Minutes of the PHQ branch discussion on the Kerala question; Draft resolution on the India-China border dispute.
    - Draft Resolution, 1958; 5.93.1
    - Amendments to the Constitution By-K.G.Srivastava and Others, 1958; 5.93.2
    - P.B. Circular No. 1,2&3/58, 1958; 5.93.3
    - 19-2-58 Cell Secretary and General Body Meeting, 1958; 5.93.4
    - P.H.Q. Conference Details in the Month of March, 1958; 5.93.5
    - 16-5-58 Letter to All Members of the National Council and Provincial Committee, 1958; 5.93.6
    - 26-12-58 Letter to P.H.Q. Branch Mmbers By-Mohit Sen, 1958; 5.93.7
    - 19-1-59 Letter to P.H.Q. Branch Mmbers On Formation of Party Groups By-Mohit Sen, 1959; 5.93.8
    - 16-3-59 On Formation of Party Groups, Amendments to Constitution & Central Office Branch Meeting, 1959; 5.93.9
    - August, 59 P.H.Q. Branch General Body Documents, 1959; 5.93.10
    - Brief Minutes of Discussion, Correspondence & Other Documents, 1959; 5.93.11
    - Letter to P.H.Q. Group Leaders, Agenda & Resolution, 1959; 5.93.12
    - Amendments to the Draft Resolution, 1959; 5.93.13
    - Draft Resolution on the India-China Border Dispute, 1959; 5.93.14
    - Amendment to Com. Chippu's Resolution on India-China Border's Dispute, 1959; 5.93.15
    - Entry Form in Single Page, 1959; 5.93.16
  - AITUC Center Sect. 1959
    Correspondence between G.L. Nanda and S.A. Dange; Conclusions of the meeting for introduction of automatic looms in the textile industry; Correspondence of the Jamshedpur Mazdoor Union to labour minister; Letters written to AITUC Centre from various unions; Papers of Andhra Cement Company Employees Union; Charter of Demands of millworkers in Vyavar, Rajathan and other unions; Documents related t the strikes and retrenchment in Collieries.
    - Correspondence for the month of November, 58, 1958; 5.1004.1
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of December, 58, 1958; 5.1004.2
    - Correspondence for the month of January, 59, 1959; 5.1004.3
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of February, 59, 1959; 5.1004.4
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of March, 59, 1959; 5.1004.5
      English / Telgo
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of April, 59, 1959; 5.1004.6
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of May, 59, 1959; 5.1004.7
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of June, 59, 1959; 5.1004.8
    - Correspondence and other Documents for the month of July, 59, 1959; 5.1004.9
  - AITUC Center, 1959
    Constitution of the Metal & Engineering workers federation, Bombay state; Resolutions passed in the national conferences of the All India Engineering Workers Federation; Dcuments, correspondence and circulars related to the All India Engineering Workers' Federation; Note on the history of the dispute between the Kirlosker Oil Engines Ltd. and the Engineering Kamgar Sabha; Report on the industrial disputes in Enginerring sector in Bombay.
    - Metal & Engineering Workers Federation Bombay State, 1959; 5.262-II.1
    - Note on Metal Engineering and other topics, 1959; 5.262-II.2
    - 29-6-59 Preparatory Committee, Letter for Dear Brothers, 1959; 5.262-II.3
    - Short History of the Dispute and various Correspondence, 1959; 5.262-II.4
      English / Hindi; Pune
    - Various Correspondence and Circulars in the month of August, 59, 1959; 5.262-II.5
    - General Engineering Employees' Union, Resolutionand various Correspondence, 1959; 5.262-II.6
    - 3-10-59 Letter to Shri Shantilal Shah, Honb. Min.for Labour & Law, Govt. of Bombay, 1959; 5.262-II.7
    - 18-11-59 Letter to Dear Com. Tamhane, 1959; 5.262-II.8
    - Regarding selection of workers going to East Germany for Training in Tech. line and various Correspondence in the month of December, 59, 1959; 5.262-II.9
  - Party & AITUC
    Copy of the speech of S.A. Dange on Indo-China dispute given in Bihar; Documents related to the parliamentry group of the CPI; Correspondence between S.A. Dange and various workers' unions, state and district committees of CPI; Correspondence between S.A. Dange and various other communist leaders like Sajjad Zaheer, E.M.S. Namboodaripad, Muzaffar Ahmad, Bhupesh Gupta, Abdus Sattar, P.C.. Joshi, Ajoy Ghosh, Jyoti Basu and others; Circular for CPI state committees related to the railway workers' movement; Brief report on the preparation for Mansoon session, 1959; Strike action in plantation sector; Press statements issued by the CPI; Statement issued by the Manipur state executive committee of CPI; CPI note on the Pak-US pact; Documents, bills, criculars and reports related to the Kerala following the formation of state government by the CPI; UP state CPI pamphlet on food crisis and price rise in the state.
    - 8-12-59 Bihar Rajya Council, 1959; 5.96.1
    - 19-12-59 Dear Com. Sajjad Zaheer, 1959; 5.96.2
    - 29-8-59 Pichore Parganaa Committee, 1959; 5.96.3
      Hindi; Dabra
    - 1-9-59 Comrade E.M.S. Namboodaripad, 5.96.4
    - 29-8-59 Dear Com. Dinkar Mehta, 1959; 5.96.5
    - 3-8-59 My Dear Dange, 1959; 5.96.6
    - 27-7-59 Press Statement, 1959; 5.96.7
    - 14-8-59 S.A. Dange, 1959; 5.96.8
    - 23-8-59 Dear Com. Bhupnesh Gupta, 1959; 5.96.9
    - 19-8-59 Telegram, Require text.., 1959; 5.96.10
    - 8-6-59 By Hand, Dinkar Mehta, 1959; 5.96.11
      English; Ahmedabad
    - 6-8-59 Sri Abdus Sattar, 1959; 5.96.12
    - Note of the Discussion, 1959; 5.96.13
    - 2-8-59 Brief Report on the Preparations for Monsoon Session, 1959; 5.96.14
    - 19-8-59 By Hand, Com. Dihider, 1959; 5.96.15
    - 19-08 By hand Com. Jagannath Sircar, 1959; 5.96.16
    - 13-8-59 Com. Gopinath, 1959; 5.96.17
    - 22-7-59 for favour of publication, 1959; 5.96.18
    - 27-6-59 Resolution of CEC of Communist party of India on Kerela, 1959; 5.96.19
    - 13-7-59 Com. Sarkar, 1959; 5.96.20
    - 8-7-59 S.A. Dange, 1959; 5.96.21
    - 7-7-59 The communist party of India, 1959; 5.96.22
    - 27-6-59 Hrishi Banerjie, 1959; 5.96.23
    - 11-6-59 For Publication, 1959; 5.96.24
    - 7-6-59 For Publication, 1959; 5.96.25
    - Telegram, hands of kerolday, 1959; 5.96.26
    - 2-6-59 Com T.L., 1959; 5.96.27
      English; Warnagal, Hyderabad
    - 27-5-59 Com. P.K. Thakur, 1959; 5.96.28
      English; Madhya Pardesh
    - 18-5-59 Statement issuedby.., 1959; 5.96.29
      English; Imphal
    - Notice, on 1st june, 1959; 5.96.30
    - Adhikari Communist Party, 1959; 5.96.31
    - 16-5-59 Com. Mohit Sen, 1959; 5.96.32
    - 11-5-59 Com. Khandkar, 1959; 5.96.33
    - 17-4-59 The Haryana Sewa Ashram, 1959; 5.96.34
      English; Rohtak
    - 25-4-59 Comrade S.A. Dange, M.P., 1959; 5.96.35
      English; Jalpaiguri
    - 15-4-59 S.A. Dange, 1959; 5.96.36
    - 12-4-58 Amendments to the Political Resolution, 1958; 5.96.37
    - 30-3-59 Secretary Indian Communist Party, 1959; 5.96.38
      English; Kerala State
    - 20-3-59 P.R., 1959; 5.96.39
    - Com. Vallabha Rao, 1959; 5.96.40
      English; new Delhi
    - 11-3-59 the Secreratry, 1959; 5.96.41
    - 5-5-59 On party Fund Levy, 1959; 5.96.42
    - 10-3-59 Telegram, On 9th Ajoy Ghosh, 1959; 5.96.43
    - 6-5-59 By hand, Circular, 1959; 5.96.44
    - 6-3-59 On Pak-U.S. Pact, 1959; 5.96.45
    - The Chief Minister, 1959; 5.96.46
    - 9-3-59 Punjab State Council, 1959; 5.96.47
      English; Jullundur
    - Com. Surjeet's Letter to Minister for Irrigation and Power, 1959; 5.96.48
      English; Chandigarh
    - Copies of Telegram, 1959; 5.96.49
    - 6-3-59 Comrade Dange, 1959; 5.96.50
    - 5-3-59 Com. Dange, 1959; 5.96.51
    - 4-3-59 Telegram, Pick up, 1959; 5.96.52
    - 24-2-59 Somnath Lahiri, 1959; 5.96.53
    - 2-3-59 Telegram, 108, 1959; 5.96.54
    - The Chief Officer (confidential), 1959; 5.96.55
    - 23-2-59 Com. K.G. Srivastava, 1959; 5.96.56
    - 24-12-58 Com. S.A. Dange, 1958; 5.96.57
    - 20-2-59 Com. Dange, 1959; 5.96.58
    - 1/3-11-58 On the anniversary of the twelve parties declaration, 1958; 5.96.59
    - 22-2-59 Express Delivery, 1959; 5.96.60
    - 22-2-59 By Hand, Secretary, 1959; 5.96.61
    - 21-2-59 Com. Farooquri, 1959; 5.96.62
    - 16-2-59 Utkal State Committee, 1959; 5.96.63
      English; Cuttack, New Delhi
    - 13-1-59 S.A. Dange M.P., 1959; 5.96.64
    - 14-2-59 Com. M.N., 1959; 5.96.65
    - 17-1-59 General Secretary, 1959; 5.96.66
    - 8-1-59 Com. K.G., 1959; 5.96.67
      English; Jabalpur
    - 2-2-59 Com. Dange, 1959; 5.96.68
    - 5-1-59 The Chief Electrel Officer, 1959; 5.96.69
      English; Pondicherry
    - 16-1-59 Com. S.A. Dange M.P., 1959; 5.96.70
    - Telegram, 242, 1959; 5.96.71
    - 30-12-58 Comrades Srivastava & Achutan, 1958; 5.96.72
      English; Vijayawada
    - 18-12-58 Mr. Dange, 1958; 5.96.73
    - Katihaar ke dono Jute Mil, 1958; 5.96.74
      Hindi; Katihaar
    - 23-12-58 Com. S.A. Dange, 1958; 5.96.75
      English; Calcutta, Bombay
    - 16-12-58 For Favour of Publication, 1958; 5.96.76
    - 26-1-59 The Secretary Lok Sabha, 1959; 5.96.77
    - 27-12-58 Review of the work of the communist group, 1958; 5.96.78
    - 16-1-59 Com. PCJ, 1959; 5.96.79
    - 20-1-59 Com Dange, 1959; 5.96.80
      English; Allahbad
    - 12-1-59 Achutan, 1959; 5.96.81
    - 12-1-59 Comrade Dange, 1959; 5.96.82
    - 10-1-59 Com. Kali Shankar, 1959; 5.96.83
    - 18-12-58 Com. K.G. Sriwastava, 1958; 5.96.84
    - 16-1-59 Telegram Nagpur.., 1959; 5.96.85
    - 31-12-58 M.Veerabhadram, 1958; 5.96.86
      English; Visakhapatnam
    - 22-9-58 Com. S.A. Dange, 1958; 5.96.87
    - 20-10-58 A Letter of Appeal, 1958; 5.96.88
      English; Japan
    - 8-12-58 The Daily Nawan Zamana, 1958; 5.96.89
      English; Jullundur, New Delhi
    - 20-9-58 Shilong Local Committee, 1958; 5.96.90
      English; Shilong
    - 19-9-58 Co. Dange Bans, 1958; 5.96.91
      Hindi; Chiplun
    - 1-9-58 Com. Dange, 5.96.92
    - 4-9-58 Com. S.A. Dange, 1958; 5.96.93
    - 30-8-58 Com. S.A. Dange M.P., 1958; 5.96.94
    - 26-8-58 Profit sharing bonus for the year 1957/58, 1958; 5.96.95
      English; Burnpur
    - Vurnpur Kulti ke Shramik Karamchariyon se appeal, 1958; 5.96.96
      Hindi/ Bangauli; Burnpur
    - 19-8-58 Taher Hossain Saheb, 1958; 5.96.97
    - 16-12-58 Com. Jyoti Basu, 1958; 5.96.98
      English; New Delhi, Calcutta
    - 16-12-58 Balachandran, Com. Phani Bora, Com. Dange, 1958; 5.96.99
    - 3-12-58 Com. S.A. Dange, 1958; 5.96.100
    - Minutes, Letter & On Levy Question during Dec/58, 1958; 5.96.101
    - Letters During Nov/58, 1958; 5.96.102
      English; Giridih, New Delhi, Rajasthan, Ambala, Bhanjnagah
    - 25 Agust se Communist Party ka Rajyavyapi Andolan, 1958; 5.96.103
      Hindi
    - Letter & India Press Agency during Oct/58, 1958; 5.96.104
    - Telegrams, Letters & Court Suit during Sep/58, 1958; 5.96.105
      English; Jaipur, New Delhi, Poona, Bombay, Calcutta, Alleppey
    - Information Document on Monopolies, Letters & Telegrams & Confidential by Bhupesh Gupta during Aug/58, 1958; 5.96.106
      English; Patna, New Delhi, Jaipur, Meerut, Trivandrum, Kanpur
    - Press Conference, 1958; 5.96.107
    - Jagadhri ke Sahanti, 1958; 5.96.108
    - For Immediate Release, letters & Resolution during July/58, 1958; 5.96.109
      English; Jamshedpur, New Delhi, Lucknow
    - Letters on Progress of preparatory work and others during June/58, 1958; 5.96.110
      English; Darjeeling, New Delhi
    - Letter to S.S. Dange, 1958; 5.96.111
    - Letters Under Certificate Posting, To all members of NCPC, copy of telegrams and others, 1958; 5.96.112
      English; Bombay, Amritsar, New Delhi, Vazirabad
    - Letters, telegrams & Resolutions during April/58, 1958; 5.96.113
      English; Madras, Bombay, New Delhi, Amritsar
    - Telegrams, Letters, Insurance Employee Party Committee during March/58, 1958; 5.96.114
      English/ Hindi; Amritsar, Darjeeling, Cuttack, New Delhi, Calcutta, Sambalpur, Nasik, Trivendrum
    - Letters during Feb/58, 1958; 5.96.115
      English/ Hindi; Ernakulam, Calcutta, New Delhi
    - Telegram, Program Schedule, Letter, 1958; 5.96.116
      English; Ambala, New Delhi, Kozhikode, Asansol
    - Note on Insurance Party Committee & Letter During Aug/57, 1957; 5.96.117